(Video) Nicholas Negroponte: Can we switch to the video disc,
(فيديو) نيكولاس نيجروبونتي:
I'm really interested in how you put people and computers together.
أنا جد مهتم بطرق ربط الناس بالحواسيب.
We will be using the TV screens or their equivalents
سنستعمل شاشات التلفاز أو ما يشابهها
for electronic books of the future.
للكتب الإلكترونية بالمستقبل.
Very interested in touch-sensitive displays,
جد مهتم بشاشات اللمس
high-tech, high-touch, not having to pick up your fingers to use them.
والتقنية العالية والحساسية العالية
There is another way where computers
هناك طريقة أخري حيث تلمس الحواسيب الناس:
Suddenly on September 11th,
فجأة في 11 من سبتمبر
the world got bigger.
أصبح العالم أكبر.
NN: Thank you. (Applause)
نيكولاس نيجروبيتي: شكراً لكم. (تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
When I was asked to do this,
عندما طُلِب مني أن أفعل هذا
I was also asked to look at all 14 TED Talks
طُلِب مني أيضاً مشاهدة جميع محادثات TED الأربعة عشر
that I had given,
التي قمت بتقديمها
chronologically.
بتسلسل زمني.
The first one was actually two hours.
في الحقيقة، استغرقت أول محادثة ساعتين.
The second one was an hour,
الثانية ساعة واحدة، ثم نصف ساعة،
and all I noticed was my bald spot getting bigger.
و كل ما لاحظته هو ازدياد حجم صلعتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Imagine seeing your life, 30 years of it, go by,
تخيلوا مشاهدة مرور 30 سنة من حياتكم،
and it was, to say the least,
و كانت على الأقل
for me, quite a shocking experience.
برأيي ،تجربة صادمة.
So what I'm going to do in my time
لذا ما سأفعله الآن هو محاولة مشاركة ما حدث
during the 30 years,
خلال 30 سنة الماضية،
and then also make a prediction,
بالإضافة لتقديم بعض التوقعات
and then tell you a little bit
و بعد ذلك أخبركم قليلاً
about what I'm doing next.
عما سأفعله بعد ذلك.
And I put on a slide
وأعرض لكم مقطع
where TED 1 happened in my life.
لأول محادثة TED في حياتي.
And it's rather important
وهو أمر مهم نوعاً ما
because I had done 15 years of research before it,
لأني كنت قد راكمت 15 سنة من الأبحاث قبلها،
so I had a backlog, so it was easy.
مما جعل الأمر سهلاً.
It's not that I was Fidel Castro
لم أكن أستطع الكلام كفيدل كاسترو لساعتين،
or Bucky Fuller.
أو كبوكي فولر.
I had 15 years of stuff,
لقد تراكمت لدي أمور لـ 15 سنة،
and the Media Lab was about to start.
و مختبر الميديا الذي كان علي وشك البدء.
So that was easy.
لهذا كان الأمر سهلاً.
But there are a couple of things
لكن هناك بعض الأشياء
about that period
عن تلك الفترة وعما حدث
One is that
الأولى هي
it was a period when computers
أنها كانت حقبة حيث
weren't yet for people.
لم يمتلك الناس بَعْدُ الحواسيب.
And the other thing that sort of happened
و الشئ الثاني الذي حدث إلي حد ما
during that time is that
خلال هذا الوقت هو
we were considered sissy computer scientists.
أننا كنا نعتبر علماء حاسوب تافهين.
We weren't considered the real thing.
لم نكن نعتبر كشيء مهم.
So what I'm going to show you is, in retrospect,
لهذا ما سأريكم إياه، في وقت لاحق،
a lot more interesting and a lot more accepted
كان جد مثير للاهتمام وجد مقبول
than it was at the time.
عما كان عليه الحال آنذاك.
So I'm going to characterize the years
لذا سأحدد السنوات
and I'm even going to go back
بل وسأعود إلى بعض أعمالي الأولى،
and this was the kind of stuff I was doing in the '60s:
وهذا بعض ما كنت أفعله في الستينيات:
very direct manipulation,
تحكم جد مباشر،
very influenced as I studied architecture
تأثرت جدا بدراستي للهندسة المعمارية
by the architect Moshe Safdie,
على يد المعماري موشى صفدي،
and you can see that we even built robotic things
و كما ترون أننا حتي بنينا أشياء آلية
that could build habitat-like structures.
تستطيع بناء هياكل تشبه المنازل السكنية.
And this for me was
ولم يكن هذا بعد مختبر الميديا،
but was the beginning of what I'll call
لكن كان بداية ما سأسميه الحوسبة الحسية،
and I pick fingers
وقد اخترت نوعا ما الأصابع
Papers were published
حيث نشرت مقالات
about how stupid it was to use fingers.
عن مدى غباء استخدام الأصابع.
Three reasons: One was they were low-resolution.
لثلاثة أسباب: أولاً، لأنها ذات دقة منخفضة.
The other is your hand would occlude
ثانيا لأن يدك قد تغطي
what you wanted to see,
ما تريد أن تراه،
and the third, which was the winner,
وثالثا، وكان هو الفائز،
was that your fingers would get the screen dirty,
هو أن أصابعكم ستوسخ الشاشة،
and hence, fingers would never be
وبالتالي، لن تكون الأصابع أبداً
a device that you'd use.
أداة يمكنكم استخدامها.
And this was a device we built in the '70s,
وهذا جهاز بنيناه في السبعينيات،
which has never even been picked up.
والذي لم يتم بيعه قط.
It's not just touch sensitive,
ولم يكن حساس للمس فقط، بل للضغط أيضا.
(Video) Voice: Put a yellow circle there.
(فيديو) صوت: ضع دائرة صفراء هناك.
NN: Later work, and again this was before TED 1 —
نيكولاس: أعمال لاحقة، قبل محادثة TED الأولى —
(Video) Voice: Move that west of the diamond.
(فيديو) صوت: حرك هذا غرب الماسة.
Create a large green circle there.
ارسم دائرة خضراء كبيرة.
Man: Aw, shit.
رجل: أوه، تباً.
NN: — was to sort of do interface concurrently,
نيكولاس: كان نوعاً من التفاعل المتزامن،
so when you talked and you pointed
عندما تتكلمون و تشيرون
and you had, if you will,
و لديكم، إن أردتم قنوات متعددة.
Entebbe happened.
في عام 1976، حدثت عملية عنتيبي.
taken to Entebbe,
أخدت لمدينة عنتيبي،
and the Israelis not only did an extraordinary rescue,
و لم يقم الإسرائيليون بعملية انقاذ استثنائية فحسب،
they did it partly because they had practiced
هم قاموا بذلك إلى حد ما لأنهم تمرنوا على نموذج حسي للمطار.
because they had built the airport,
لأنهم أنشأوا المطار،
so they built a model in the desert,
بنوا نموذجاً في الصحراء،
and when they arrived at Entebbe,
وعندما وصلوا لعنتيبي،
they knew where to go because they had actually been there.
عرفوا كيف يتحركون لأنهم كانوا هناك من قبل.
The U.S. government asked some of us, '76,
طلبت الحكومة الأمريكية من بعضنا، سنة 1976،
if we could replicate that computationally,
إن كنا نستطيع أن نمثل العملية حاسوبياً،
and of course somebody like myself says yes.
وبالطبع فإن شخص مثلي يجيب بنعم.
Immediately, you get a contract,
إذ على الفور تحصل على عقد
Department of Defense,
من وزارة الدفاع،
and we built this truck and this rig.
وبنينا هذه الشاحنة والمقطورة.
We did sort of a simulation,
وقمنا بنوع من المحاكاة،
because you had video discs,
لأنكم تشاهدون الفيديو
and again, this is '76.
ومرة أخرى، كان هذا في عام 76.
And then many years later,
و بعد بسنوات عديدة،
you get this truck,
تحصلون علي هذه الشاحنة،
and so you have Google Maps.
فأصبح لديكم خرائط جوجل.
Still people thought,
ومع ذلك كان هناك من لم يعتقد،
and it was a man named Jerry Wiesner,
وكان رجل يدعى جيري ويزنر،
who happened to be the president of MIT,
الذي صادف أنه رئيس معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية
who did think it was computer science.
آمن بأنها من علوم الحاسوب.
And one of the keys for anybody
وإحدى المفاتيح التي يحتاجها أي شخص
who wants to start something in life:
يَوَد البَدء بأمرِ ما في هذه الحياة:
Make sure your president is part of it.
التأكد من جعل رئيسك جزء منه.
So when I was doing the Media Lab,
عندما كنت أعمل بالمختبر الإعلامي
it was like having a gorilla in the front seat.
كنت كمن لديه غوريلا بالمقعد الأمامي.
If you were stopped for speeding
لو تم توقيفكم بسبب السرعة
and the officer looked in the window
وأطل الضابط من النافذة
and saw who was in the passenger seat,
ورأى من بمقعد الراكب
then, "Oh, continue on, sir."
ثم "حسناً، أكمل طريقك سيدي."
And so we were able,
وبهذا كان بمقدورنا،
and this is a cute, actually, device, parenthetically.
وبين قوسين، هذا جهاز لطيف في الحقيقة.
This was a lenticular photograph of Jerry Wiesner
هذه صورة عدسية لجيري ويزنر
where the only thing that changed in the photograph
حيث الشئ الوحيد الذي تغير في الصورة
were the lips.
كانت الشفاه.
So when you oscillated that little piece
لذا عندما تحركون تلك القطعة الصغيرة
of lenticular sheet with his photograph,
من الورقة العدسية مع الصورة،
it would be in lip sync
فإنها تتزامن مع الشفة
with zero bandwidth.
عند عرض نطاق صفر.
It was a zero-bandwidth teleconferencing system
لقد كان نظام مؤتمرات عن بعد بعرض نطاق صفر
at the time.
في ذلك الوقت.
So this was the Media Lab's —
كان هذا المختبر الإعلامي —
this is what we said we'd do,
هذا ما قلنا أننا سنفعله،
that the world of computers, publishing,
أن عالم الحواسيب والنشر وغيرها ستجتمع معاً.
Again, not generally accepted,
مرة أخرى، لم تلقى قبولاً لدى الجميع،
And this is really where we were headed.
وكان هذا هو هدفنا الحقيقي.
And that created the Media Lab.
وهذا أدى إلى إنشاء المختبر الإعلامي.
One of the things about age
إن من الأمور الإيجابية لتقدمي بالعمر
is that I can tell you with great confidence,
هي أنه يمكنني أن أخبركم بثقة كبيرة،
I've been to the future.
بأني كنت بالمستقبل.
I've been there, actually, many times.
في الواقع، كنت هناك مرات عديدة.
And the reason I say that is,
والسبب وراء إخباركم بذلك هو،
how many times in my life have I said,
كم من مرة بحياتي قلت فيها،
"Oh, in 10 years, this will happen,"
"سيحدث هذا في 10 سنوات،"
and then 10 years comes.
ثم تأتي 10 سنوات.
And then you say, "Oh, in five years, this will happen."
ثم تقول "سيحدث هذا في 5 سنوات."
And then five years comes.
ثم تأتي 5 سنوات.
So I say this a little bit with having felt
أعترف بأن لدي بعض الشيء شعور
that I'd been there a number of times,
بأنني كنت هناك عدة مرات،
and one of the things that is most quoted
ومن الأمور الأكثر اقتباساً عني هي قولي
is that computing is not about computers,
بأن الحوسبة لم تعد متعلقة بالحواسيب فقط،
and that didn't quite get enough traction,
ولكنها لم تلقى بداية صدى إيجابي،
and then it started to.
لكنها لقيته فيما بعد.
that the medium wasn't the message.
بأن الوَسِيلة ليست هي الرسالة.
And the reason I show this car
والسبب في عرضي لهذه السيارة،
in actually a rather ugly slide
والواقع أنها صورة قبيحة،
is just again to tell you the kind of story
هو إخباركم مرة أخرى بنوع من القصص
that characterized a little bit of my life.
التي تميز نوعاً ما حياتي.
This is a student of mine
كتب أحد من طلابي
It was in the early days of GPS,
وذلك ببدايات نظام تحديد المواقع،
the car knew where it was,
كانت السيارة تعرف مكان تواجدها،
and it would give audio instructions
وتقدم تعليمات صوتية للسائق،
to the driver, when to turn right, when to turn left and so on.
متى ينعطف يميناً أو يساراً وغير ذلك.
Turns out, there are a lot of things
وتبين أن هناك الكثير من الأمور
in those instructions that back in that period
في تلك التعليمات التي كانت تمثل تحدياً
were pretty challenging,
في تلك الفترة،
like what does it mean, take the next right?
كالمقصود، بالانعطاف إلى اليمين القادم؟
Well, if you're coming up on a street,
حسناً، إن كنتم مقبلين على شارع،
the next right's probably the one after,
فالمرجح أن اليمين المقبل هو ذاك بعد الأول،
and there are lots of issues,
وهناك الكثير من المشاكل،
and the student did a wonderful thesis,
والطالب قدم أطروحة رائعة،
and the MIT patent office said "Don't patent it.
وقال مكتب براءات الاختراع بالمعهد
It'll never be accepted.
لم يُقْبَل أبداً.
The liabilities are too large.
المسؤوليات كبيرة.
There will be insurance issues.
ستكون هناك مشاكل تأمينية.
Don't patent it."
لا تعطوه براءة اختراع."
So we didn't,
لذا لم نقم بذلك،
but it shows you how people, again, at times,
لكن هذا يوضح لكم كيف أن الناس، مرة أخرى،
don't really look at what's happening.
أحياناً، لا ينظرون لما يحدث.
Some work, and I'll just go through these very quickly,
بعض الأعمال، سأمر عليها بسرعة،
a lot of sensory stuff.
الكثير من الأجهزة الحسية.
You might recognize a young Yo-Yo Ma
قد تتعرفون على يويو ما الشاب
and tracking his body for playing
وهو يحرك جسده خلال العزف
the cello or the hypercello.
التشيللو أو الكمان الجهير.
These fellows literally walked around like that at the time.
كان هؤلاء الزملاء يتمشون بهذا الشكل وقتها.
It's now a little bit more discreet
لكن الآن أصبح الأمر أكثر سرية
and more commonplace.
وشُيُوعا.
And then there are at least three heroes
كما أن هناك على الأقل ثلاثة أبطال
I want to quickly mention.
أود أن أذكرهم سريعاً.
Marvin Minsky, who taught me a lot
مارفن مينسكي، الذي علمني الكثير
about common sense,
عن الإدراك السليم،
and I will talk briefly about Muriel Cooper,
وسأتحدث باختصار عن موريل كوبر،
who was very important to Ricky Wurman
التي كانت جد مهمة لريكي ورمان
and to TED, and in fact, when she got onstage,
و TED، و في الحقيقة، فإنها عندما صعدت على المنصة،
she said, the first thing she said was,
قالت، أول شيء قالته كان،
"I introduced Ricky to Nicky."
"قدمت ريكي للتعرف على نيكي."
And nobody calls me Nicky
ولا أحد يدعوني بنيكي
and nobody calls Richard Ricky,
ولا أحد يدعو ريتشارد بريكي.
so nobody knew who she was talking about.
لذا لم يعلم أحد عمن كانت تتحدث.
And then, of course, Seymour Papert,
وبالطبع، سيمور بابيرت،
who is the person who said,
و هو الذي قال،
"You can't think about thinking
"لا يمكنك التفكير في التفكير
unless you think about thinking about something."
إلا إذا كنت تفكر في التفكير بشيء ما."
And that's actually — you can unpack that later.
وهذا حقيقةً — يمكنكم تفكيكها لاحقاً.
It's a pretty profound statement.
إنها مقولة عميقة جداً.
I'm showing some slides
سأريكم بعد العروض من محادثاتي
that were from TED 2,
كان هذا من TED 2،
a little silly as slides, perhaps.
ربما أنها عروض سخيفة بعض الشيء.
Then I felt television really was about displays.
ثم شعرت أن التلفاز عبارة عن عرض.
Again, now we're past TED 1,
مرة أخرى، الآن تخطينا TED 1،
but just around the time of TED 2,
لكن قبل فترة قصيرة من TED 2،
and what I'd like to mention here is,
وما أود الإشارة إليه هنا هو،
even though you could imagine
حتى لو أمكنكم تصور
intelligence in the device,
الذكاء في الجهاز،
I look today at some of the work
ألقيت نظرة على بعض الأعمال المنجزة حالية
and I think it's kind of tragically pathetic,
وأعتقد أن الأمر مأساوي نوعاً ما،
because what has happened is people take
لأن ما حدث هو أنهم يأخذون
the oven panel and put it on your cell phone,
لوح فرن ويضعونه على هاتفكم الخلوي،
or the door key onto your cell phone,
أو مفتاح الباب على هاتفكم الخلوي،
just taking it and bringing it to you,
يحملونه ويقدمونه لك فقط،
and in fact that's actually what you don't want.
والواقع أن هذا ما لا تريده أنت.
You want to put a chicken in the oven,
تود أن تضع دجاجة في الفرن،
and the oven says, "Aha, it's a chicken,"
وأن يقول الفرن، "آآه، هذه دجاجة،"
and it cooks the chicken.
ثم يطبخ الدجاجة.
"Oh, it's cooking the chicken for Nicholas,
"آه، إنه يطبخ الدجاجة لنيكولاس،
and he likes it this way and that way."
وهو يحبها بتلك الطريقة."
So the intelligence, instead of being in the device,
لذا بدلاً من وضع الذكاء في الجهاز،
we have started today
بدأنا حالياً
to move it back onto the cell phone
بوضعها على الهاتف الخلوي
or closer to the user,
أو أقرب من المستخدم،
not a particularly enlightened view
ليست هذه بنظرة مستقبلية
of the Internet of Things.
في إنترنت الأشياء.
Television, again, television what I said today,
نعود إلى التلفاز،
that was back in 1990,
كان هذا في سنة 1990،
and the television of tomorrow
وكان تلفاز المستقبل
would look something like that.
يبدو بهذا الشكل.
Again, people, but they laughed cynically,
مرة أخرى، ضحك منه الناس بتشكك،
they didn't laugh with much appreciation.
لم يضحكوا عليه ولو ببعض التقدير.
Telecommunications in the 1990s,
الإتصالات في التسعينيات،
George Gilder decided that he would call this diagram
قرر جورج جيلدر أن يسمي هذا الرسم البياني
the Negroponte switch.
بتقاطع نيجروبونتي.
I'm probably much less famous than George,
وأنا على الأرجح أقل شهرة من جورج،
so when he called it the Negroponte switch, it stuck,
لذا عندما أعطاه ذلك الاسم، ظلّ عليه،
but the idea of things that came in the ground
لكن فكرة إنترنت الأشياء التي خرجت للوجود
would go in the air and stuff in the air
نمت وأعطت ثمارها
would go into the ground
وانتشرت
has played itself out.
وأثبتت نفسها.
That is the original slide from that year,
هذا هو العرض الأصلي لتلك السنة،
and it has worked in lockstep obedience.
ونجح الأمر بشكل سَلِس.
We started Wired magazine.
أطلقنا مجلة وايرد.
Some people, I remember we shared
أتذكر أننا تشاركنا مع بعض الناس
the reception desk periodically,
مكتب الاستقبال بشكل دوري،
and some parent called up irate that his son
وقد اتصل أحد الأباء الغاضبين لأن ابنه
had given up Sports Illustrated
قد ترك مجلة سبورت إلوسترايتد
to subscribe for Wired,
من أجل الاشتراك بوايرد،
and he said, "Are you some porno magazine or something?"
وقال، "هل أنتم مجلة إباحية أو غيرها؟"
and couldn't understand why his son
لم يستطع استيعاب أن يكون ابنه
would be interested in Wired, at any rate.
مهتما بوايرد، بأي شكل من الأشكال.
I will go through this a little quicker.
سأتخطى هذا بشكل أسرع.
This is my favorite, 1995,
هذا هو المفضل لدي، 1995،
back page of Newsweek magazine.
الصفحة الأخيرة من مجلة نيوزويك.
["Nicholas Negroponte, director of the MIT Media Lab, predicts that we'll soon buy books and newspapers straight over the Internet. Uh, sure." —Clifford Stoll, Newsweek, 1995]
"يتوقع نيجروبونتي، أننا قريباً سنقتني الكتب والصحف مباشرة من الإنترنت.
at least it gives me pleasure
عليكم الاعتراف بأن هذا يجعلكم على الأقل يجعلني أنا أشعر بالسعادة
when somebody says how dead wrong you are.
عندما يقول أحدهم كم كنت على خطأ.
"Being Digital" came out.
ثم صدر "كن رقمياً".
For me, it gave me an opportunity
بالنسبة لي، لقد قدم لي فرصة
to be more in the trade press
لولوج عالم تجارة الصحافة
and get this out to the public,
وإخراج ذلك للجمهور،
and it also allowed us to build the new Media Lab,
وسمح لنا ببناء مختبر الميديا الجديد،
which if you haven't been to, visit,
والذي أنصحكم بزيارته إن لم تفعلوا،
because it's a beautiful piece of architecture
لأنه قطعة معمارية جميلة
aside from being a wonderful place to work.
بغض النظر عن كونه مكان رائع للعمل.
So these are the things we were saying in those TEDs.
وهذا ما كنا نقوله بمحادثات TED.
[Today, multimedia is a desktop or living room experience, because the apparatus is so clunky. This will change dramatically with small, bright, thin, high-resolution displays. — 1995]
[ستصبح الوسائط المتعددة شاشات عرض متقدمة] أتينا إليهم.
I looked forward to it every year.
انتظرت رداً على ذلك كل سنة.
It was the party that Ricky Wurman never had
كانت الحفلة التي لم يحظى بها ريكي أبداً
in the sense that he invited many of his old friends,
إذ دعا العديد من أصدقائه القدامى،
including myself.
ومن بينهم أنا.
And then something for me changed
ثم حدث معي تغيير عميق.
I became more involved with computers and learning
أصبحت أكثر انشغالاً بالحواسيب وبالتعليم
and influenced by Seymour,
وتأثراً بسيمور،
but particularly looking at learning
ولكن بالتركيز على التعليم
as something that is best approximated
كأفضل مقاربة
by computer programming.
لبرمجة الحاسوب.
When you write a computer program,
عندما تكتبون برنامج حاسوب،
you've got to not just list things out
لا يكون عليكم فقط إعداد قائمة بالأمور
and sort of take an algorithm
ونوع من الخوارزميات
and translate it into a set of instructions,
وترجمتها إلى مجموعة من التعليمات،
but when there's a bug, and all programs have bugs,
لكن عند حدوث خطأ، وجميع البرامج بها أخطاء،
you've got to de-bug it.
يكون عليكم تصحيحها.
You've got to go in, change it,
يكون عليكم الدخول وتغييرها،
and then re-execute,
ثم إعادة تنفيذها،
and you iterate,
فتكررون العملية،
and that iteration is really
وهذا التكرار هو بالفعل
a very, very good approximation of learning.
مقاربة جيدة للتعلم.
So that led to my own work with Seymour
وهذا يقودني للحديث عن عملي مع سيمور
in places like Cambodia
بأماكن مثل كمبوديا
and the starting of One Laptop per Child.
وانطلاق مشروع حاسوب لكل طفل.
Enough TED Talks on One Laptop per Child,
وقد استقبل TED محادثات عديدة عنه،
so I'll go through it very fast,
لذا سأمر بسرعة عليه،
but it did give us the chance
لكن هذا أعطانا الفرصة
to do something at a relatively large scale
للقيام بشيء على نطاق واسع نسبياً
in the area of learning, development and computing.
بمجال التعليم والتنمية والحوسبة.
Very few people know that One Laptop per Child
القليل من الناس يعرفون بأن حاسوب لكل طفل
was a $1 billion project,
كان مشروعاً بقيمة مليار دولار،
and it was, at least over the seven years I ran it,
وكان، على الأقل خلال السنوات 7 التي أدرته،
but even more important, the World Bank
لكن الأهم، أن مساهمة البنك الدولي
contributed zero, USAID zero.
والوكالة الأمريكية للتنمية الدولية كانت 0.
It was mostly the countries using their own treasuries,
والمثير للاهتمام، أن الدول وفرت معظمها
which is very interesting,
باستخدام سندات خزائنها،
at least to me it was very interesting
وبرأيي على الأقل، هو مثير
in terms of what I plan to do next.
بالنظر لما أنوي فعله بعد ذلك.
So these are the various places it happened.
هذه هي المناطق التي استفادت من المشروع.
I then tried an experiment,
وقد حاولت بعدها القيام بتجربة،
and the experiment happened in Ethiopia.
أنجزتها بإثيوبيا.
And here's the experiment.
وهذه هي.
The experiment is,
التجربة هي،
can learning happen where there are no schools.
هل يمكن التعلم دون مدارس.
And we dropped off tablets
قدمنا لابتوبات "حواسيب لوحية" للأطفال
with no instructions
دون تعليمات لتشغيلها
and let the children figure it out.
وتركناهم يحاولون معرفة كيف تعمل.
And in a short period of time,
وفي فترة قصيرة،
they not only
لم يقوموا فقط
turned them on and were using 50 apps per child
بتشغيلها واستخدام 50 تطبيقا للأطفال
within five days,
خلال خمسة أيام،
they were singing "ABC" songs within two weeks,
بل حفظوا أناشيد "الأبجدية" في أسبوعين،
but they hacked Android within six months.
ولكنهم قرصنوا أندرويد في 6 أشهر.
And so that seemed sufficiently interesting.
وقد كان ذلك جد مثير للاهتمام.
This is perhaps the best picture I have.
وربما هذه أفضل صورة لدي.
The kid on your right
الطفل على يمينكم
has sort of nominated himself as teacher.
يبدو أنه عَيَّنَ نفسه كأستاذ.
Look at the kid on the left, and so on.
انظروا إلى الطقل على اليسار، وإلى من معه.
There are no adults involved in this at all.
ليس هناك تدخل للراشدين تماماً.
So I said, well can we do this
لذ، تساءلت، إن كان بإمكاننا
at a larger scale?
أن نقوم بذلك على نطاق واسع؟
And what is it that's missing?
فما الذي ينقصنا؟
The kids are giving a press conference at this point,
بهذه الصورة الأطفال يتناقشون،
and sort of writing in the dirt.
ويبدو أنهم يكتبون على الأرض.
And the answer is, what is missing?
والجواب هو، ما الذي ينقصنا؟
And I'm going to skip over my prediction, actually,
والحقيقة أني لن أخبركم بتوقعاتي
because I'm running out of time,
لأنه لم يعد لدي متسع من الوقت،
and here's the question, is what's going to happen?
والسؤال هو، ما الذي سيحدث؟
I think the challenge
أظن أن التحدي
is to connect the last billion people,
هو أن ربط آخر مليارشخص بالشبكة،
and connecting the last billion
وربط آخر مليار
is very different than connecting the next billion,
هو أمر جد مختلف عن ربط المليار المقبل،
and the reason it's different
والسبب مختلف
is that the next billion
لأن المليار المقبل
are sort of low-hanging fruit,
يسهل ربطه،
but the last billion are rural.
بينما أن آخر مليار موجود بالقرى.
Being rural and being poor
وكونه قروي وفقير
are very different.
هو أمر جد مختلف.
Poverty tends to be created by our society,
يميل الفقر ليكون نتاج لمجتمعنا،
and the people in that community are not poor
والناس بذلك المجتمع ليسوا فقراء
in the same way at all.
بنفس الشكل بالمرة.
They may be primitive,
ربما أنهم بسطاء جداً،
but the way to approach it and to connect them,
لكن طريقة التقرب إليهم وربطهم،
the history of One Laptop per Child,
وتاريخ حاسوب لكل طفل،
and the experiment in Ethiopia,
والتجربة بإثيوبيا،
lead me to believe that we can in fact
تقودني لأؤمن بأنه يمكننا في الواقع
do this in a very short period of time.
أن نقوم بذلك في فترة قصيرة.
And so my plan,
وكانت خطتي هي،
and unfortunately I haven't been able
وللأسف لم أستطع
to get my partners at this point
إقناع شركائي بهذه النقطة
to let me announce them,
لأقول لهم،
but is to do this with a stationary satellite.
بأنه علينا فعل ذلك بقمر صناعي ثابت.
There are many reasons
هناك العديد من الأسباب
that stationary satellites aren't the best things,
التي لا تجعل منها أفضل فكرة،
but there are a lot of reasons why they are,
ولكن هناك أخرى تقول عكس ذلك،
and for two billion dollars,
ومقابل ملياري دولار فقط،
you can connect a lot more than 100 million people,
يمكنكم ربط أكثر من 100 مليون شخص،
but the reason I picked two,
لكن السبب لاختياري مليارين فقط،
and I will leave this as my last slide,
وسأختم بهذه النقطة،
is two billion dollars
أن ملياري دولار
is what we were spending
هو ما نصرفه
in Afghanistan
بأفغانستان
every week.
في كل أسبوع.
So surely if we can connect
لذا من المؤكد أنه إن كنا قادرين على ربط
Africa and the last billion people
أفريقيا وآخر مليار شخص
for numbers like that,
بمبلغ كهذا،
we should be doing it.
فينبغي أن نفعل ذلك.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Stay up there. Stay up there.
كريس أندرسون: تفضل بالبقاء هناك.
NN: You're going to give me extra time?
نيكولاس: هل ستعطوني وقتاً إضافياً؟
CA: No. That was wickedly clever, wickedly clever.
كريس: لا. قد كان ذلك ذكياً بخبث، ذكي بخبث.
You gamed it beautifully.
لعبتها بالشكل الصحيح.
Nicholas, what is your prediction?
نيكولاس، ما هو توقعك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
NN: Thank you for asking.
نيكولاس: شكراً على سؤالك.
I'll tell you what my prediction is,
سأخبرك بتوقعي،
and my prediction, and this is a prediction,
وهو، وهذا هو توقعي،
because it'll be 30 years. I won't be here.
لأنه بعد 30 سنة. لن أكون هنا.
But one of the things about learning how to read,
لكن مما أعيبه على طريقة تعلمنا للقراءة،
we have been doing a lot of consuming
أننا استهلكنا الكثير
of information going through our eyes,
من المعلومات باستخدام أعيننا،
and so that may be a very inefficient channel.
وربما أنها طريقة غير فعالة كما يجب.
So my prediction is that we are going to ingest information
لذا أتوقع بأننا سنتناول المعلومات
You're going to swallow a pill and know English.
ستبتلعون حبة وتتعلمون الإنجليزية.
You're going to swallow a pill and know Shakespeare.
وحبة أخرى فتعرفوا شكسبير.
And the way to do it is through the bloodstream.
وذلك عن طريق مجرى الدم.
So once it's in your bloodstream,
وبمجرد أن تصل مجرى دمكم،
it basically goes through it and gets into the brain,
ستتوجه رأساً نحو دماغكم،
and when it knows that it's in the brain
وعندما ستصل إلى الدماغ
in the different pieces,
وإلى مختلف الأماكن به،
it deposits it in the right places.
ستضع تلك المعرفة بالمكان الصحيح.
So it's ingesting.
المستقبل هو البلع.
CA: Have you been hanging out with Ray Kurzweil by any chance?
كريس: هل ترافق ري كرزويل، ربما؟
NN: No, but I've been hanging around with Ed Boyden
نيكولاس: لا، لكني أرافق إد بويدن
and hanging around with one of the speakers
ومع واحد من المتحدثين بـ TED
who is here, Hugh Herr,
الحاضر هنا،
and there are a number of people.
وهناك العديد من الأشخاص.
This isn't quite as far-fetched,
ذلك ليس ببعيد، 30 سنة من الآن فقط.
CA: We will check it out.
كريس: سنتأكد من ذلك.
We're going to be back and we're going to play this clip 30 years from now,
سنشاهد هذا الفيديو بعد 30 سنة،
and then all eat the red pill.
وبعدها سنتناول الحبة الحمراء.
Well thank you for that.
أشكرك على ذلك.
Nicholas Negroponte.
نيكولاس نيجروبونتي.
NN: Thank you.
نيكولاس: شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)